Guide to the Valley Migrant League Records 1962-1972
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Valley Migrant League Records
1962-1972
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Coll 30
Valley Migrant League (Woodburn, Or.)
2 linear ft. 1 document case, 1 oversize folder
Small quantity of records of an organization that worked to improve economic opportunities, housing, health care, and education for migrant farm workers in the Willamette Valley of Oregon.
Historical Note
The Valley Migrant League (VML), which was founded in 1964, was first funded in May 1965 by the Office of Economic Opportunity as part of Great Society anti-poverty programs to serve migrant farm workers in the Willamette Valley of Oregon. It operated programs until the mid-1970s.
The VML established its administrative headquarters in Woodburn, with Area Opportunity Centers in Aumsville, Dayton, Hillsboro, Independence, Salem, Sandy, and Woodburn. Initially, the board and administration was predominately non-farm worker, but by 1967, more than half of the board was composed of seasonal or ex-seasonal farm workers. By 1968, farm workers dominated the VML's operations.
Other Valley Migrant League programs included adult education through evening classes, Winter Day Schools, and existing community schools; publication of a newspaper, Opportunity News (and later Relampago); job development, counseling and placement; housing; and child care centers.
The records are composed primarily of printed materials that were separated from the Valley Migrant League Photographs (Organized Lot 74) at the Oregon Historical Society Research Library. The collection provides episodic coverage of VML activities, including its first published annual report to the executive board (1967). The collection also includes materials on the National Farm Workers Association and United Farm Workers Organizing Committee strikes and grape boycott assembled by the Valley Migrant League, 1966-1972. These materials document boycotts and farm worker support events in Portland and Eugene, Oregon. Included is a flier advertising a public rally at Portland State University featuring Cesar Chavez, organizer and leader of the farm worker unions, as well as extensive materials on the strikes and boycotts against Di Giorgio Corporation of California and Safeway stores.
The collection is arranged into the following series:
Series A: Valley Migrant League and Related Materials, 1962-1970
Series B: Farm Workers Strikes and Boycotts, 1966-1972
The collection is open to the public.
The manuscript collection was separated from the Valley Migrant League Photographs (Organized Lot 74) at the Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
The Stella Maris House Records (Mss 1585) at the Oregon Historical Society Research Library include approximately one linear foot of Valley Migrant League Records; among these are board minutes and reports, 1965-1970. The Research Library Serials Collection includes bound volumes of the Opportunity News, 1965-1967, and six unbound issues for 1968.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Chavez, Cesar, 1927-
Citizens Farm Labor Committee (Portland, Or.); Di Giorgio Corporation.; National Farm Workers Association.; United Farm Workers Organizing Committee.; United States. Office of Economic Opportunity.; Valley Migrant League (Woodburn, Or.); Western Region Conference of OEO Migrant Projects (1st: 1967: Woodburn, Or.)
Aumsville (Or.); Dayton (Or.); Hillsboro (Or.); Independence (Or.); Salem (Or.); Sandy (Or.); Willamette Valley (Or.); Woodburn (Or.)
Boycotts--Oregon.; Hispanic Americans--Oregon.; Migrant agricultural laborers--Oregon.; Occupational training--Oregon.; Strikes and lockouts.
Oregon; Agriculture; Labor History; Mexican Americans
Broadsides.; Fliers.
Reports.
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Valley Migrant League and Related Materials, 1962-1971; Series A
  - Conferences—programs, 1962, 1967 (Box-folder 1/1)
    USDA Land and People Conference, Portland, Oregon, 1962 October 1-2
    First Western Region Conference of OEO Migrant Projects, Woodburn, Oregon (sponsored by Valley Migrant League), 1967 June 7-9
  - Ephemera, circa 1967 (Box-folder 1/2)
    Opportunity Card (blank) entitling holder to services at Opportunity Centers (English and Spanish)
    Leaflets advertising VML job training and placement programs
  - News releases and clippings, 1966, undated (Box-folder 1/3)
    "What Do We Know About the Valley Migrant League?"—typescript release and clippings as it appeared in the Woodburn Independent, 1966 December 29
    Handwritten draft of news release, "VML Housing," undated
  - Opportunity News—correspondence re. microfilming the newspaper, 1967 January (Box-folder 1/4)
  - VML Project Report, 1967 (Box-folder 1/5)
    Annual report to the board covering the period 1966 January 1 through 1967 March 31. Includes board and staff, introduction to the background and funding of the organization, and description of programs. Illustrated with photographs.
  - Related publications, 1965, [1971] (Box-folder 1/6)
    Pamphlet, "Su Seguor Social" (in Spanish only). Washington, D.C.: Social Security Administration, 1965 December
    Pamphlet, "The Condition of Farm Workers and Small Farmers in 1970." New York: National Sharecroppers Fund, [1971]
- Farm Workers Strikes and Boycotts, 1966-1972; Series B
  - National Farm Workers Association (NFWA)—Di Giorgio strike and boycott, 1966 (Box-folder Oversize Folder)
    Boycott support cards produced by the NFWA, [1966]
    Leaflets and circular letter produced by Citizens Farm Labor Committee (Portland, Oregon), [1966]
    University of Oregon Farm Workers' Committee information packet, including bibliography, news release, sample letter to Robert Di Giorgio, and boycott information, including broadside (oversize), [1966]
    Newsletter, ILWU 40 Recap, Supercargoes and Checkers Union (Portland, Oregon), special bulletin in support of the NFWA strike, 1966 June 1
    Newletters (2), 1965 June
  - United Farm Workers Organizing Committee (UFWOC / AFL-CIO), [1966]-1972 (Box-folder 1/8, Over B-1)
    Broadside (oversize) re. AFL-CIO boycott of Di Giorgio products, [1966]
    Fliers, newsletter, pledge form, postcard, and circular letters—Portland Boycott Committee of UFWOC, 1969. Includes flier advertising public rally at Portland State University featuring Cesar Chavez as speaker.
    Letter and receipt from UFWOC, Delano, California, to Harold and Barbara Vatter, Portland, Oregon, recognizing contribution, 1969
    Flier, Second Statewide Poor People's Conference, Council of the Poor, Eugene, Oregon (English and Spanish)
    Open letter to Senator Mark Hatfield from Oregon Farm Workers asking him to oppose legislation outlawing boycotts.Part of a Good Friday demonstration organized by Catholic clergy at Portland, 1972